Guide to the Joseph Brandt Scrapbooks ALBA.236
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Joseph Brandt Scrapbooks
1936-1992
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Brandt, Joseph, 1909-1997
ALBA.236
3 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
Joseph Brandt (1909-1997) fought in the Spanish Civil War as a member of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade during 1937 and 1938. He was a dedicated member of the Communist Party throughout his life, joining the Young Communist League in 1926, working as an organizer in the 1930s, and later serving as a longtime member of the CPUSA national committee. He kept a number of scrapbooks in which he collected a broad range of materials relating to the Spanish Civil War, and especially American participation in the War. The scrapbooks consist of a widely diverse collection of correspondence, reports, clippings, photographs, flyers, pamphlets and typescript drafts of articles by Brandt and others. Materials documenting the role of African-Americans in the Lincoln Brigade were probably collected and used by Brandt for a pamphlet he produced on that subject in 1979.
Provenance
This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Born Sam Brustein in Poland in 1909, Joseph Brandt immigrated to New York City at the age of fifteen and joined the Young Communist League two or three years later. He was working in Ohio as an organizer for the Communist Party in 1937, but soon joined the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in response to the Communist International's appeal for volunteers. Brandt took part in several well-known engagements during the Spanish Civil War, including the attempt to warn Loyalist troops of the Gandesa-Batea fascist offensive in March of 1938 and the late-night covert operation in which Robert Merriman and David Doran lost their lives. Brandt himself was wounded by enemy fire twice, during the retreat from Gandesa and then in an offensive around the area of Quatro Camisos. He returned to the United States in December of 1938.
On his return, Brandt married Sylvia Opper, whom he had met during a Works Progress Administration (WPA) strike in Cleveland. He continued to organize for the Communist Party's District 6 in Ohio. During World War II, he served as a paratrooper in the joint U.S.-Canadian special forces unit known as the "Devils Brigade," carrying out commando missions behind Nazi lines in France. After the war, he remained active in the Communist Party and was forced to go underground to avoid prosecution under the Smith Act, but was eventually arrested by the FBI and served six months in jail. Brandt served on the national committee of the CPUSA for many years and remained an active member until his death in July of 1997 at the age of 87.
Brandt was especially concerned with documenting and publicizing the contributions of the African-Americans who fought in the International Brigades. In 1979, with the help of a group of Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB) members and New Outlook Publishers, he produced a pamphlet titled Black Americans in the Spanish People's War against Fascism, 1936-1939.
Scope and Content Note
The 16 scrapbooks are not clearly organized with regard to chronology or subject, but a few have a discernible overall focus. Scrapbook 11 contains mostly material on Spanish Civil War prisoners in Spain, and Scrapbook 14 relates to the publication of Brandt's pamphlet on African-Americans in the Lincoln Brigade. The bulk of the collected material consists of clippings, printed ephemera and copies from books and periodical articles about the Spanish Civil War with emphasis on the International Brigades, some from the period and some later. Included is a wide range material giving biographical details of individual U.S. volunteers; notable are pamphlets, clippings and photocopies of confidential Party reports (addressed to John Williamson) relating to volunteers from Ohio, Brandt's home state (see Scrapbook 9). The scrapbooks also contain items concerning the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade's support for progressive forces in Nicaragua and VALB anniversary celebrations. There is a small selection of letters to Brandt, and some photographic prints (some unlabeled, others distributed in Spain by the International Brigades authorities).
In the detailed descriptions of individual scrapbooks below the contents are grouped in categories (letters, records, publications, photographs) within each scrapbook entry, rather than being listed in the order of their appearance in the scrapbook itself. The entries do not list every item in each scrapbook, but summarize notable material. Within each folder scrapbook contents are arranged in their original order. Scrapbooks have been dis-bound, but the covers, with typed labels by JB, have been retained.
Arrangement
The pages of each scrapbook occupy a separate folder. The folders, and materials within each folder, are organized according to the original sequence of scrapbooks, rather than chronologically or alphabetically.
The files are grouped into one series:
Missing Title
I, Scrapbooks
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Scrapbooks.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Research (document genres).; Correspondence.; Biography files.; Black-and-white photographs.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Foreign public opinion.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x African Americans.; Drafts (documents); Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Prisoners and prisons.; Articles.; Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV; Brandt, Joseph, 1909-1997; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Brigada Internacional, XV--Biography; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade
- Series I: Scrapbooks
  - Clippings re: African-Americans in the Spanish Civil War (SCW), general; Salaria Kee (a.k.a. Salaria Kea, later O’Reilly) Typescript re: Oscar Hunter Program: "Tribute to the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade," Avery Fisher Hall, Apr 7, 1986, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Typescript: " ‘This Ain’t Ethiopia, But It’ll Do’: African-Americans and the Spanish Civil War," Robin D. G. Kelley (1990); also correspondence between Kelley and JB Typescripts: "Modern Spain: A Factual Outline," Lowry Field (1944); Partial list of volunteers in Lincoln and Washington Battalions: Brunete, Jarama Front Clippings re: Vaughan Love; Kenneth Frederick Nelson; Donald Rochon Maps: Jarama offensive; Brunete offensive; Aragon offensive Sheet music: "Tell It On and On!," Edith Segal (1974) Pamphlet: The Negro People and the Soviet Union, Paul Robeson (1950), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - [Scrapbook titled "The Spanish People’s Struggle" on spine] Pamphlets: The Crime of Francisco Franco; 30 Caricaturas de la Guerra, Ministero de Propaganda de la República Española Original photos (3, black and white): Spanish peasants; soldier with rifle, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Typescripts: "On the Threshold of Changes," Dolores Ibárruri (translation); "The Phantom Pilot of the Phantom Brigade," Joe Mizrahi; "The Black Volunteer in the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: The Beginning of a Bibliography" Pamphlet: ¡No Pasaran!: The 50th Anniversary of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Periodicals: Mundo Obrero Vol. 12, no. 11 (1989), re: Dolores Ibárruri; Spanien Heute(1986), re: 50th Anniversary of ALB; Der antifaschistische Widerstandskämpfer, Vol. 7 (1986), re: 50th Anniversary of ALB Programs: "Memories of Spain," concert given by returning veterans on RMS Aunsonia, Dec 16, 1938; "Tribute to the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade," Avery Fisher Hall, Apr 7 1986 Clippings re: Oliver Law; Jim Peck; Paul Williams, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters: Yo Kawanari with JB (1985) re: Japanese volunteer "Jack" (Yoshio?) Shirai; JB personal correspondence, incoming and outgoing (1985; 1987; 1992) Program and materials: Westchester People’s Action Coalition (WESPAC) Peace and Justice Award, Al Warren (1991) Clippings re: ALB 50th Anniversary (1986-1987); ALB 45th Anniversary; Bill Bailey; Anthony DeMaio; Ralph Fasanella; John Field; Ralph Field; Moe Fishman; Sydney Harris; Charles Nusser; Paul Robeson; William Susman; Cesar Vallejo; Marion Wachtel, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Typescripts: "The Struggle for a Democratic Spain," JB and Al Kent; "Brief Resume on Veterans of the ALB," JB; "US Investments in Spain," Victor Perle (1961); "Origin and Cause of the People’s War against Fascism in Spain…," two lectures given at People’s School for Marxist Studies (1983); "The Revolt of the Fascist Military"; "Spain: End of the Franco Era?," JB (1963) Franklin D. Roosevelt, copied excerpt from a statement on Spain (during WWII); various statements on U.S. relations with post-SCW Spain; VALB bulletins Pamphlet: Speech given by Enrique Carlos de la Casa, Jul 19, 1937 Articles on U.S. and the Franco regime, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Periodicals and pamphlets: Le Volontaire de la Liberté, No. 8 (Jul 1937); Letters from the Trenches from Our Boys in Spain; Two Years of American Aid to Spain: The Story of the Medical Bureau and North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy(1938?); Among Friends, Spring 1938 Map: Spain, notations in pen Original photos (2, color): ALB veterans marching in parade; Charles Nusser at French memorial to volunteers of International Brigades, Fuencarel, Spain (1983) Photocopied photographs of volunteers Clippings: International Brigades, various; a group labeled "pictures cut out from a book from the Franco Fascist Regime", undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Typescripts: "Spain," Emmet J. Hughes (1955); copy of "The United States of America and the Cause of the Spanish Republic – 1936-1939," Arthur Landis Announcement of course: "The Spanish Civil War and its International Impact," New School for Social Research, Fall 1981 Pamphlet: "These Americans Say, ‘Lift the Embargo Against Republican Spain’" (1939) Periodicals: World News and Views Vol. 19, no. 27 (May 1939) re: Czechoslovakia; International Press Correspondence Vol. 16 No. 20 (Apr 1936) re: Spain Poster: "The Good Fight", undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Programs: "People’s Unity Rally," welcoming returned veterans from Spain, Cleveland, OH, Jan 22, 1939; "Homenaje a los veteranos de la Brigada Lincoln," Casa de España, New York, NY, Nov 1986 Records: Communist Party assessments of returned Ohio SCW veterans (photocopies): 1939 Flyers: US Committee for a Democratic Spain(1978); "Return to Spain" trip organized by Center for International Studies and Estudios Historicos de la Guerra Civil Española(1983) Clippings re: Communist Party of Ohio; Cuba; Ernest Hemingway; "Fascist propaganda"; William Herrick; Oliver Law; Monument to American Volunteers in Spain (Spanish Civil War Historical Society); Ronald Radosh; Francisco Garcia Salve; "Spain’s Heroism – Lesson in the Fight Against Aggression," JB (1939); USSR press releases re: Spain (1977-1979), undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Proclamations: "Captain Oliver Law and Nelson Mandela Day," Apr 24, 1988, Manhattan; "Oliver Law and ALB Day," Nov 21, 1987, Chicago Typescripts: "The 25th Anniversary of the Spanish Civil War"; "1979 Bibliography of the Spanish Civil War" Flyers: "The Good Fight"; "Malraux-Hemingway: Embattled Spain," symposium, Boston College (1990) Periodicals: Political Affairs(Aug 1986), re: "International Brigades against War and Fascism 1936-1986" Copy of letter re: planning of VALB Dinner; dispute over invited speaker Dr. Goodlet’s public remarks on Zionism, and protest again inviting him from Zionist members of VALB, 1979 [from Ruth Davidow?] Clippings re: Bill Bailey; Alvah Bessie; Bill McCarthy; Spanish/Latin American poetry of Spanish Civil War (SCW) period; "To Die in Madrid," 1966 documentary; reviews of SCW-themed books, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - [Mostly material on prisoners of war in Spain] Letters: Carl Geiser to JB re: Cuba; re: Prisoners of the Good Fight; Jacob K. Javits to JB; JB personal correspondence Typescripts include: "Statement to the United Nations by Second Latin American Conference on Amnesty for Political Prisoners and Exiles of Spain and Portugal"; "A Report on Civil Rights and the Position of Political Offenders in Spain," compiled by group of international lawyers after 1960 visit to Madrid; "The Unknown Soldier as a Symbol of the Spanish Civil War," speech given by Charles Nusser at 47th Annual VALB Celebration; "Statement of the World Federation of Democratic Youth Bureau on the Murder of the Spanish Democrat and Patriot, Julian Grimau"; "International Volunteers/Former Members of the Spanish Republican Army Now in Concentration Camps," Felix Kusman, director of Campaign for International Volunteers Records: Communist Party assessments of four released ALB prisoners: Fred Borer, Edward Johnson, Claude Pringle, Herman Carl Riffe Pamphlets: Spanish Political and Religious Prisoners, Alfred G. Tucker; Mensaje a la Asemblea de las Naciones Unidas, Primera Conferencia Sudamericana Pro Amnistía para los Presos y Exilados Políticos de España y Portugal(1960), undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Typescripts: Speech given by Sister Benedicta, OSH (daughter of Ramon Sender) for 46th Anniversary of ALB; "Homage to the Lincoln Battalion," Casa de España, New York, NY, 50th Anniversary of ALB, Nov 8 1986; "Address to the 50th Anniversary Dinner of the ALB," speech given by John L. Hess, Apr 5, 1987 Letters: translations of letters to VALB from: A. Osipenko, Spanish Group of Soviet Veterans (1984); Boris Smirnov, Chairman of the Section of the Participants of Spanish Anti-fascist [sic] (1975) House Resolution (Hawaii) honoring ALB on 50th anniversary of founding (1987); notes to JB from Moe Fishman, 1984 and Miguel Gascon, 1989 Articles: George Seldes, "Franco’s Sixth Column ," The Fight, 1938; New York Times Magazine, "The Fight for Peace and Democracy," Apr 1938 Clippings and publicity material re: "The Good Fight"; Guernica; Spanish Civil War 50th Anniversary Pamphlet: ¡No Pasaran!: The 50th Anniversary of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters: "Report on Three Spanish Organizations," Moe Fishman to VALB; JB correspondence with: Alvah Bessie (1980); Ruth M. Decker (1973); Milt Felsen; Carl Geiser (1988); Boris Smirnov (1976?); A. L. Tanz (1986) Periodical: Volunteer for Liberty(Nov 1946) Flyer and speech re: Memorial meeting honoring City College students, alumni and teachers who volunteered in the Spanish Civil War, Apr 13, 1980 Clippings re: Chinese volunteers; Ralph Fasanella; Raleigh Frohman; Ben Goldring; George Kaye; Clement Markert; Saul Wellman, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters re: JB pamphlet Black Americans in the Spanish People’s War against Fascism(Note hand-written letter from Pete Seeger) Periodicals: Journal of the Lincoln Brigade (15th Annual; 10th Annual) Flyers re: John Tisa; James Yates Clippings re: African-American ALB veterans, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letters: Fredericka Martin with JB (1979-1980); Carl Geiser to JB re: Cuba Typescripts: "Heroines of the Good Fight," Frances Patai (1989); "Report by Charles Nusser and Steve Nelson" re: future role of VALB (n.d.); "Internationalism in Action: The Book Scene," Willi Weinert, Party CC Archives, Communist Party of Austria Flyer re: Our Fight, ed. Alvah Bessie and Albert Prago Periodicals: Historical Commission Bulletin; William Winter Comments(Jul 1986) Clippings re: Nicaragua; "To Die in Madrid," 1966 documentary, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - [Scrapbook titled "Spain 1936-1939" on spine] Covers of publications: Spain(Oct 1934); Internationella Brigaden, Lise Lindbæk; Prisoners of the Good Fight, Carl Geiser Card: " Freiheit für Spaniens Patrioten" Original photos (18, black and white): Soldiers (no battles); war victims; property damage; Spanish people and daily life Clippings: Pictures from Spanish Civil War, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)